[SPEAKER_01]: Is it wrong to judge others?
[SPEAKER_01]: And are we supposed to be aiming for that non-judgmental attitude towards everything?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abstaining from a judgment is your judgment.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you're judging it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question is not whether you should not judge others.
[SPEAKER_00]: The question is whether you should do it with or without ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is not that you judge and discriminate.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the nature of mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts are already forms of discrimination.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want this, I don't want that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like whether you... whether they're fueled by ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you don't want.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're factually judging the behavior of some person, that is... that is a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if on account of that fact, you feel superior, start involving your conceit, you feel they're inferior, again start involving your conceit, you feel righteous, you feel ill-will, hatred, irritation towards them, that's why you're wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because there is a thought of judging and discriminating between agreeable, disagreeable, right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: But...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's it's harder to differentiate problem on that level, because it's more personal and more kind of unpleasant as well, and also more ambiguous to work on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your conceits and, like, whatever, emotional background of it, it's much harder than to just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, I'll just remove the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just will not judge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that now makes you sacrifice your own intellect, your own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then what?
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't judge the clearly immoral, unwholesome, deluded behavior?
[SPEAKER_00]: You pretend it's fine, because you didn't know how to deal with the problem of it that you were experiencing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just a lazy attempt of trying to deal with the issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to recognize the mind judges.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yourself and others, that's what the mind does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Picks and chooses, indiscriminates.
[SPEAKER_00]: But do you feel superior on account of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, don't feel superior on account of your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't feed them, don't entertain them, don't indulge them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you feel ill-will on account of your thoughts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't welcome it, don't entertain it, don't indulge it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you just have thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, if that thought was fueled solely by your ill-will, once you stop fueling the ill-will, the thought will disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if the thought was also factual recognition of the state of affairs, in terms of this person's behavior or that person's behavior, your ill-will will disappear, but the recognition of reality will not disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they are behaving like a foolish, immoral person.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't want to associate with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wish them all the best.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have any ill-will or hatred.
[SPEAKER_00]: or wishing harm and cruelty, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean you're a blinded fool now, that doesn't discriminate between different types of behavior, different types of people, different sets of values in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's the encouragement to really be able to define what is wholesome and unwholesome, and not to deny that those are factors that need to be discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if something is wholesome or unwholesome, you are responsible in how you feel about it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your feelings, they make you act.
[SPEAKER_00]: They make you do stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are you restrained in regard to your feelings, or do you feel fully justified in regard to them?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that kind of sense of righteousness, when people are, like, righteously indignant and full on ill-will, but they fully feel righteous and wholesome, because this behavior is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but that doesn't justify the extent of your ill-will now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That behavior is wrong in itself, full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where it ends.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you feeling superior, having your will on account of it, that will never be justified by any behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the point, as the Buddha would say, even if highway robbers are sawing your limbs, one by one, extremely unjust behavior,
[SPEAKER_00]: Killing you, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have cruelty and ill-will towards them, you have not fulfilled the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean, oh, it's fine for them to cut your limbs.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you hating them is a completely separate thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only person who is not free from ill-will, person who hasn't fulfilled the dhamma, will jump into.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, passion, ill-will, distraction, delusion is something you are always responsible, regardless of the circumstances that are pressuring, seemingly pressuring you into it.